[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank defreitis
and welcome to holotalk the internet's
laser and holography talk show enjoyed
in over 42 countries throughout the
world and now here's this week's show
[Music]
hello good morning is this Dave
how are you Dave it's Frank de Freitas
hello Frank how are you doing good
yeah it's real nice we're on a global
scale we're practically Neighbors
how are you today this morning pretty
good pretty good are you up for doing a
show sure
and I'm sure everyone's interested in
learning about this dichromate
holography that you do
which I had mentioned in one of the
emails uh these people that work with
dichromater like Wizards
yeah you have to be uh a person likes to
Tinker a lot that's for sure yeah well
let me ask you this with it being so
easy to just pick up the phone and have
a box of silver halide plates delivered
to
our doors and pop them in a plate holder
and do an exposure what's the attraction
to dichromate for you
um the overall brightness you can really
achieve uh and um uh the ability that I
don't have to buy any any films
basically can make our own and that has
a real Advantage as long as
it's good
you know you have to get you know you
got to get your your coating down and
you got to get you know your exposure's
all really uh for every batch you really
have to adjust and you know once you can
pass those hurdles
then it's uh you know you kind of say to
yourself well why do I have to go get
them well there's a totally difference
between films yeah silver hairline is
much more you know
set um and you end up with a lot less
noise what like what laser are you using
for this dichromate there uh well I have
I have uh I got a couple layers but the
one I'm particularly
fond of these days is is the coherent
it's 100 100 milliwatts with uh you know
532 nanometer output and the thing has
got I don't know me
coherence to it so wow you know it
really uh you know you throw away your
string when you start playing around
with this thing and you have to measure
up you know beam paths and
stuff like that it really I don't know
to me it's like the Cadillac you know
yeah that's that's the laser that folks
were talking about that's available from
one of the shops online right correct
yeah Mr Gizmo
yeah
he uh I believe it's got a few of them
left you know and that that runs pretty
much out of the box after you receive it
yeah I guess I'm kind of going for my
memory but I think it was a 24 uh bulk
power supply DC power supply I see and
uh yeah you just plug that little sucker
in and off it goes I had to remove the
out of a
I don't know a box
a box a couple other servos in a wave
plate and
I provided a little
big fan on it
um because it does it does get a little
hot so they recommend to keep cool you
know it's been running I've had it what
almost two years now wow and uh
great
it's great it's running right now in the
basement as a matter of fact so you're
exposing this dichromate that you put
together with green am I correct correct
yeah yeah Jeff Blythe has uh
John Paul uh well they proposed a a
newer more sensitive recipe
which I did some trials with it it
seemed to work out real well I had I
kind of how you Vamp everything in order
to
to get it to work
consistently
but you know that's what it's all about
especially with dye cream dichromate is
you really have to take
little baby steps as I call them when
you're making a change because you make
one change and five different things
seems to look different you know so yeah
many years ago there was a holography
studio in Philadelphia down by the
Delaware River and it was Douglas Miller
holographic design I believe they used a
he-cad laser down there
they had a coding room where they would
coat the plates and they would pass it
through a little hole in the wall
and the person would take the Hologram
and expose it and then the person would
code another plate pass it through the
hole in the wall it seemed like a a very
slow process
but they got wonderful results I think
most of the sizes they did were I think
up to maybe about four by five inch but
beautiful Holograms
you really start to get larger than four
by five maybe five by seven then you
really got you know other other factors
that start coming into play and at least
with my 100 100 milliwatt laser you know
probably if I had an Argon a couple of
watt argon or something like that it
would it would certainly behave a little
bit differently but it's uh you know for
the hobbyist it's a great laser to use
and and
um it uh
you know it's always a challenge with
this thing I don't know if you've seen
Sally uh Weber's Holograms she recently
had a nice display at uh the whole of
Center in New York and she had some you
know really good size programs I'm I'm
not sure but they were you know probably
60 by 30 or 60 by 40 centimeters and
apparently she was shooting her H2S in
her basement with the same same coherent
oh I see it's quite versatile you know
yeah
but uh yeah getting back to the
dichromate it's uh you know it's kind of
one of those Hobbies I don't recommend
it for anybody but once you
if you will
uh it really is uh satisfying
on a scale of one to ten
compared to someone just doing what I
would say traditional holography where
would you say the difficulty level is I
imagine it's with the with the
formulations and the coding but I
imagine humidity and everything plays a
role in it doesn't it
it all comes to play and you know uh you
know probably the coding because that's
where it initially starts off the
formulas you have a lot to you can kind
of refer to in books and and
articles online Etc so you can kind of
keep trying but yeah you know you'll
have everything going along really good
one day uh then you go downstairs the
next day and you shoot something and
there's nothing's working so you got to
say let's see was it the weather
you know let's see now was there rust in
the bath water who knows what it is so
you know then you have to be able to say
okay where did things go wrong and start
back from scratch again so
so you lose your way it can be call to
come back and they're very frustrating
you know so you really I mean my coding
when I first got my the 315 laser I
spent six months or eight months in my
kitchen coating pieces of glass with
just gelatin to try and get the the
proper the proper procedure yeah
and um finally was able to you know get
to a point where I'm satisfied with my
coating is it a relatively safe process
well you know the ammonium dichromate uh
is a toxic uh chemical for sure and then
uh well is it similar to potassium
dichromate yeah yeah
the ammonium dichromate any of the
dichromates uh you know heavy metal yeah
yeah so you know you want to neutralize
anything before you uh you know put it
down the sink which I don't recommend
really anybody doing I do my best not to
put anything in the ground
and then um you know you also have hot
alcohol bath uh some some guys that have
multiple hot alcohol baths that's never
a really fun thing to have you know
without ventilation and yeah
possibly the fire always exists so you
have to be careful with that but you
know past all those hurdles it's a great
hobby you know as long as you don't burn
down the your house you're okay how long
have you been doing this with dichromate
I'm sorry how long have you been doing
this with dichrome well you know it's
funny my inspiration many years back 15
years back is I uh I had the chance to
go work with Lee Lacy who's a really
good holographer and an excellent you
know extremely excellent dichromate
philographer and um
uh worked for just a couple days with
him and he was just enough to inspire me
that
blue laser well in those days it was a
blue laser yeah I would
I would uh take the plunge and then you
know lo and behold 15 20 years later
these green
Lake on you know the Surplus market for
well they were going for a thousand or
twelve now they're up I think a little
bit higher yeah
so
um I have a couple watt argon here I
have a Lex L88 it's just sitting here
yeah so I imagine I'd be in pretty good
shape if I ever wanted to give it a shot
oh absolutely yep you know if you want
to give it a shot I could send you some
plates out and you could see if you can
uh you know see what you can you can
produce yeah I don't even have it hooked
up yet it's got a like 220 triple phase
and so many gallons of water a minute
yeah that's what's that's what's so
amazing about the uh I mean the keycads
are good too
except yeah you never see them anywhere
oh yeah going downstairs and I think it
has like a coherence length of like two
centimeters or something so it's kind of
difficult you know if you're gonna do
contact copies or or proximity copies um
that would probably be the way to go
because it'll go a lot quicker but
um
um you really need something that's got
some coherence like if you're going to
do any kind of Imaging
you know holography
but uh
so I guess you I guess you where you saw
my my third place
contest
yeah it was a real screamer
it's a funny story because I you know we
were getting down to the wire and
you know I had the I had the the
lettering said and and that Master shot
and I shot the dog and that was all set
but I didn't have a background and I'm
looking around and suddenly my my wife
shows up from the supermarket she says
oh honey look at this nice defrost
I got on the on the tissue box oh no
I said give me that I cut that thing
right out and stuck it in the back and
it's amazing because
if I ran my hologram as a wide band
which means you know it
it uh will take many different
wavelengths and reflect them back that's
why you have a white dog yeah uh I found
that if I tuned it if I made the
Hologram so the dog was green then the
integrating the background was green
also but if I made it white the dog
white where it would be wide band then I
got a full rainbow out of the the
fraction grating in the back oh of
course yeah because all the all the
wavelengths were there
the one and I put that in
and here we are today but you know
thanks for the uh the whole of talk uh
MP3 disc
you're welcome it's great I
I'll plug it in and refer back to stuff
you know yeah well you'll be part of
that now yeah I guess so
yeah people uh years from now will be
listening to you talk about the dry
cremate holography well you know I I uh
last year once I got a handle on things
I put um a posting up on uh The
holography Forum and that shows
you know my simplified coding method
I've I've evolved since then but you
know for anybody who's starting off it's
a good it's a good starting place to see
what's going on and
um
every once in a while he gets people
from you know far and wide call me and
thank me or you know send the email and
thanks for putting it up there so it is
still used yeah and uh do you run any
workshops for people uh I really have it
you know I'm not set up to do that but I
suppose I could you know I know uh you
had a friend Ellie uh you sent me her
number I'll give her a call and we'll
see if we can two we can do because it's
just
it's just um mainly because especially
if it was dichromate I didn't feel I had
had enough experience under my belt well
now I think I do but yeah you know a
year ago
I'll say that
um recently
uh I I I see I think you had an
interview with Dinesh yes a patio and he
had a hologram he made and he always
intrigued me of two colored skulls you
know just the one was a green I think
one was a red and I asked him about it
and didn't really respond too much
because it was probably his proprietary
you know formula he didn't want to you
know you know tell the world about but I
think he he softened up a little bit and
I had he has a uh he has a website that
holography make sure I get it right it's
the
holographersgallery.org and
um he finally uh uh you know after I
asked him you know about this
multi-color hologram you know if you
share how it was done and sure enough he
wrote down the formula and um especially
I took it picked up the ball and started
running with it like like crazy
that's what I was doing last week I know
we had talked about
together but I really wanted to get this
under my belt yeah and um
you can see the results
there as well as you know at the
gallery.org or at a topography
forum.org under multi-colored dichromate
and you know I could post you a picture
if you want to see it but incredible the
colors are getting out of this thing if
you send a picture to me I'll put it
right on the holotalk page too sure yeah
because uh you know it's one of those
instances where all of a sudden hair was
standing up in the back of my head yeah
I'm so excited that it actually worked
for
forever I was trying to make a
multi-color dichromate Holograms and uh
lo and behold Dinesh had it
well if you had the hair standing up on
the back of your neck you're definitely
a holographer yes how long have you been
involved with holography how did you get
started
well it's the good old Museum of
Photography oh okay yeah you know back
in the day in my in my early High School
Days
I think I was probably the maybe the
first of the second year that it was
open I was a member
just ever since then I was just been
bitten by the
written by the Bee I I had a an Aerotech
like three milliwatt laser oh okay I
think between the power supply and and
Tube the the OEM tube I think it cost me
400 bucks I believe it yeah I had I had
the Aerotek five milliwatts so I know
what you're talking about yeah and uh
you know in those days you know
it was pretty much on on your own I
guess there were probably classes and
stuff but I was pretty much self-taught
so that's that's that was my my
inspiration yeah so we've just been
there you know in the back of my in the
back of my head uh you know holography's
always been part of my life I guess that
was a lot of money for those lasers back
then
oh my goodness
my mom you know because I said education
she said she said I'll buy you one you
know that was a deal
my little five milliwatt Aerotech
actually had the power supply built
right into the cylindrical housing wow
so it was just a
cylinder you know you're cylinder laser
head but at the one end it was where the
power supply was located right in the
cylindrical head and it just had a key
built right into the laser head
ER head and it was nice but I think I
may have paid I don't know 6.95 or more
for that five milliwatt well yes uh
crazy and that was that was a lot of
money I mean
three daughters you know I just moved
into a house
and uh to turn around and say 695
dollars for a laser
not even many people didn't even know
what the heck a laser was outside of
Science Fiction back then
it was uh it was it was something and
then I got the spectrophysics
uh 124b and that I actually had to take
a bank loan out and I had like 36
for 15 milliwatts
I'll tell you now you know the online
auctions and you know we know the Big E
uh I'm telling you
it's like I'm a kid in the candy store I
mean there's so many good things that
come by apparently you know all the labs
must be up
or getting government funding so all
this other Surplus
Surplus is hidden hitting the shelves if
you will
I'm having hey there here you know I
mean
um
I bought I have a laminar flow already I
bought another one here locally from a
guy for eighty dollars a four by eight
laminar flow like you know
it's just amazing you know what was one
of the one of my oh my jodon electronic
shutter okay yeah you you have a site
about Joe Don stuff and uh I'll tell you
this is
it's a an analog type shutter you know
you have to turn the knob and go to the
next but it has a Vernier gauge and it's
really great especially when I'm doing
multiple exposures because you get a
real feel
for adjustments
doing it with a dial rather than you
know saying okay I got to take 25
seconds off of this second exposure to
make this one but by using the dial
really helps out yeah analog
yeah the 1950s black and white Science
movie or something yeah well it's funny
because this shutter is a really great
shutter and it also has a detector head
and um
I remember that yeah it didn't come with
a detector head but I would love to buy
one so I said well maybe I could you
know put one together from another one
and I called up you know uh you know
over at uh
showed on
and they have no record they didn't keep
any of the electronics and I guess now
it's it's it's don don Gillespie's son
is the one taking care I think he's the
president of the company they're in
Michigan or something
he didn't I guess they didn't hold on to
that information so I'm kind of just I
mean it's a nice unit the way it is yeah
so yeah I remember years ago going over
to visit
one of my second lasers
and going into his basement and he just
had the thing was jam-packed with laser
tubes everywhere oh my goodness
underneath the stairs everywhere yeah so
it was quite an operation here
yeah I remember I was up at this
this center for advanced visual studies
up at MIT back in I believe 1985 for the
summer program
and that was back in the day when I was
making payments on this on this on this
laser
struggling to uh
be able to write it you know write a
check every month so that I could keep a
laser going
and I walked in there and they had one
section of the building
and it was just stacked about as high as
you could get stacked with uh
spectrophysics 125s and argon lasers and
Krypton lasers
and power supplies and all they were
doing all they were was just stored in
this room that were donated to the
center and I looked at that and I
thought this is just unbelievable you
know I mean trying to make a payment on
a 15 mL
and here's a whole room full of them
that no one's even touching yeah I know
I'm sure it's going there's plenty of
places like that throughout the
throughout the country yeah but yeah I
wonder why you see a heat CAD so AP on
on eBay or one of you know one of the
one of the electronic sales guys and uh
nine times out of ten because I bought a
couple of them oh really
lost all the cadmium
has all been dissipated it doesn't
really dissipate out but it becomes hard
and it goes onto the walls yeah so but I
got lucky and I got one that uh works
pretty well
what's it putting out they're not they
weren't very powerful lasers
[Applause]
watch would be nice
I'd have to uh you know take a loan out
for the electricity to run yeah
uh yeah it's nice to have a plug and
play laser come
years ago actually I did some some of my
early dichromatic work was with uh
Mort Siegel his son Mark Siegel spatial
images spatial images internet
it's over here in Long Island yeah those
names are familiar yeah I think I think
Mort Siegel was Morton Siegel he was
probably at the first Symposium on
display holography I think okay
do you sell any of your work
really I
like the art application
and smart Holograms and there's plenty
of you know security but I I was always
intrigued by the art end of it you know
you looked at the big
you know the big transmission rainbow
transmission Holograms which actually I
was gearing up to do and I ran into this
multi-colored
chromate formula now I'm back to square
one you know trying to get get a handle
on this so once I get this uh under my
belt again I'll probably go back over to
switching over the silver I keep saying
that but yeah
I just got a box of those ultimate
plates in with the chemistry yeah so
it's not open yet but I'm getting set up
to do a couple test shots with the
material uh yeah I still have you know I
still have like a box and a half of
a film left okay since I've had this
laser and I've shot hundreds of
holograms but I've yet to use a piece of
film purchase film yeah
sooner or later I'm gonna you know dim
down the lights
and go back into the Dark Ages if you
will and start shooting some red again
right in the green you know silver
highlights hey this is the this is the
perfect time of the year to experiment
with if you only have red and green you
don't have the blue this is the perfect
time of year because you can find all
these little red and green figurines for
Christmas and I did a shot the other
night with the red and green
going to the Fujifilm
okay and uh I don't know if I'm doing
something wrong I'm gonna have to
revisit it but uh
if I if I it's the the two images are in
complete registration they don't go out
out of registration but if I have it at
one angle it's it's reddish and if I
turn it and illuminate it in another
angle it's sort of green
put it in the middle it's almost white
like an open aperture hologram so I've
I've got to figure out what I'm doing
here I'm trying to get the two color
looks beautiful illuminated with the two
lasers
maybe uh okay all right so you use the
two lasers to to illuminate from
different angles no same angle I'm
combining the beam into one beam sending
it through the spatial filter and it
comes out I only have red and green I
don't have blue so it comes out it's
like a yellow
you know and the figurines
look gorgeous
no with the two colors it's like Santa
Claus sitting in a chair with an elf so
the elf's got the green costume Santa's
got the red and even the uh even the
skin tones on the little figurines you
know it sort of goes to a yellow and uh
but I just I just can't seem get it to
show up color in the single beam
reflection hologram I just don't
understand the color balancing is as I'm
flying especially with this latest
dichromate uh you can't really see it
in the present you but just by doing two
exposures and I I altered the mask in
between the two between the red and the
green because this was like a this is
almost like like where you do a tea bath
okay and
silver howl it's kind of the same
theoretical operation I guess the way it
said and uh by overlapping the red and
the green I get a really nice gold oh
but what I noticed is my I have two
figures
if you want to figure on the right was
just just paint them white at the same
time so one of the whites was just
slightly less than the other one and the
colors on the other one rather than
being red is kind of orange and yes the
other one is a light green just by
shading yes exactly a slight variation
in in exposure will change that shade
anyways I guess from if it's using a red
and green laser will be to Orange so
yeah
it's kind of uh tricky yeah there's a
lot of stuff you can do with just the
two colors yeah yeah actually I posted
up on uh the holographers gallery
[Applause]
and today we'll see you know how did I
get all these colors out of only two
exposures and and I know Dinesh knows it
but I just thought maybe somebody else
would answer in but I'll send you that
picture and you can post that yeah and
you can also if you ever have a friend
that used to do something called color
separation where you would take a color
photograph
for printing and and separated out the
cyan magenta yellow and black they'll be
they'd be able to explain very easily to
you how you get all those you know
millions of colors just uh from a few
photoshop's got that I'm sure yeah
well you have a group one is it called
Skype is that how you pronounce that we
have Skype and it's fun
[Applause]
it's fun so that's what I'm calling it
Escape okay I've never worked with it I
I've always been on Macintosh computers
and I don't think they have it available
for Mac I would say
you talk straight through the computer
you know you spend you go to Radio Shack
and a lot of local electronics spend 30
bucks and buy a microphone uh uh headset
plug-in and well currently the way we're
set up I think we could have five five
people online at once wow that's decent
um yeah you know it's it's great if if
any you know of your listeners or if you
want to join us sometimes matter of fact
we we uh at 10 30 Eastern Standard Time
10 30 a.m Saturdays
to talk so we're you know right after
we're done talking I'll I'll sign on and
I know maybe there'll be four or five
guys but you can't call in with a
regular phone though right no no can you
probably what you could do I mean you
could propose a question
um
Skype like you don't have to have
you know you can it's almost like an
instant message James oh I see yeah so
if somebody wanted to you know ask us a
question while we're all on that would
work too or just ask a question during
the week and we can answer it you know
something like that well let the
listeners know because this will be this
will go as part of the archives so
somebody may be listening to this you
know next summer next fall if someone
wanted to become part of this uh it's
it's specifically for dichromate
holography
but I think
it probably will become you know any
biography but yeah
uh my Skype address is
davevat1 d-a-v-e b-a-t-t one which
I guess that's
the Skype address if you will okay and
then there's always my uh you know just
regular my email address is Holo art
h-o-l-o-a-r-t
at AOL Dot
okay and um that you know if somebody
wanted to get into Skype group then what
they could do is uh just contact me
through
and then um you know I'll put them on
the calling list and then what happens
is it's an automatic calling list so I
just hit the button and it starts
calling everybody okay it puts them on
one at a time as a conference conference
so
[Applause]
if anybody wants to join they could
certainly get involved that way terrific
we're coming up on 30 minutes so is
there anything that you wanted to add
that I didn't ask about that you can
think of
holography Forum you know the whole
world yeah uh it was uh it was good that
it was there at a time when I was said
well too maybe I'd like to get back into
holography because I really put it down
for 10 years you know 15 years yeah and
it was sites like yours that inspired it
and I think that's what we have to you
know keep going and hopefully that's
what we're doing now you know inspiring
others well thank you for that and uh
you're certainly inspiring me to give
this dichromate holography a try after
all these years
uh it's kind
of all right well Dave thank you so much
for taking the time to come on to the
show this early in the morning
it was a late night for me last night
and a lot of driving from the
Meadowlands back and yeah
was over there for the um
Devils Penguins game
hockey and uh that's a long trip for me
to get back yeah yeah it was it was a
little over well actually it took almost
an hour to get out of the sports complex
and then about two hours to get home and
then you lay in then you lay in bed and
you're still going 80 miles an hour well
I shouldn't say that on the uh you know
65 miles an hour on the uh while you're
laying in bed
a great day great weekend and thank you
so much and I have Michael Harrison
later this morning at 11 o'clock he's
actually going to go up for this week
because he's got his new his new store
that he just opened online and I thought
it would be a good opportunity to get
him one there since it's the season
and then I'll have you on right after uh
Michael's show okay great and what I'll
do is I'll send you
out of uh the list of of the pictures
Etc and then you can put them up
wherever you want all right well thank
you so much Dave hope to meet in person
sometime
all right take care bye